Guide to the Elsa Guerdrum Allen papers, 1885-1976,
Allen, Elsa Guerdrum papers, 1885-1976
- Series II. Professional Correspondence
  - General
    - American Philosophical Society, 1936-1961 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      Includes correspondence regarding manuscript as well as grants and fellowships
    - American Philosophical Society, 1951-1961 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      Correspondence regarding the publication of The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon and submission of John Abbot Manuscript
    - Aspital, A.W., 1945-1954 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      Department of Prints and Drawings - British Museum; Includes Elsa Allen's Daily File Carbons
    - B - Correspondence, 1928-1964 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Babiy, Edith, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Books for Library, c. 1939-1959 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - British Museum - Watson, Aspital and Sawyer, 1934-1952 (Box 6, Folder 28)
      Includes notes and book requests
    - C - Correspondence, 1933-1963 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Cantwell, Robert at Sports Illustrated, 1962-1964 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Chipmunk Study Research, 1926-1964 (Box 6, Folder 31)
      Includes outline for "Studies of the Life History of the Eastern Chipmunk" by Elsa Allen
    - Cornell University General, 1918-1968 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Cornell University: Library, 1948-1964 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - D - Correspondence, 1934-1964 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - E - Correspondence, 1938-1964 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - F - Correspondence, 1935-1968 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Farquhar, S.E. - Childcraft Magazine, 1935-1939 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      Publication of early articles by Elsa Allen
    - G - Correspondence, 1935-1965 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Gay, Hazel - Librarian, American Museum of Natural History, 1939-1953 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - German Ornithologists, c. 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - H - Correspondence, 1933-1964 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Hargitt, Edward research correspondence, 1955-1960 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - History of Science Society, 1944-1947 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Isis, 1944-1951 (Box 6, Folder 43)
      Regarding abstracting the History of American Ornithology Before Audubon for Isis - Pogo, Alexander and Sarton, George
    - K - Correspondence, 1935-1963 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - L - Correspondence, 1935-1955 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Laboratory of Ornithology, 1947-1963 (Box 6, Folder 46)
      Regarding the Laboratory of Ornithology and books in its collection
    - Laboratory of Ornithology, 1955-1959 (Box 6, Folder 47)
      Includes information regarding Arthur and Elsa Allen's lecture tours and Laboratory of Ornithology Newsletters
    - Lectures by Elsa Allen, 1935-1962 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Mc-M - Correspondence, 1935-1950 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - McAtee, W.L., 1951-1956 (Box 6, Folder 50)
      Author of "A Dictionary of American Birds"
    - Minerva's Daughters, 1938-1941 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, dated and undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard University, 1936-1959 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - N - Correspondence, 1952-1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - O-P - Correspondence, 1934-1949 (and undated) (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Correspondence and Programs
    - Preussiche Staatesbibliothek regarding Prince Mortiz von Nassau-Siegen, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Farm Journal, The Quarrie Corporation and New York Zoological Society. Note on folder "EGA Biography"
    - Q-R - Correspondence, 1923-1950 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Royal Society of London, 1935-1942 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - S - Correspondence, 1929-1963 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Schoffner, Charles - The Farm Journal, 1919-1920 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Steuart, Lyman and Eleanor, 1948-1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - T-V - Correspondence, 1935-1966 (and undated) (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - W - Correspondence, 1934-1965 (and undated) (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence X-Z, 1935-1954 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Daily File, 1946-1947 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Daily File, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Daily File, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Daily File, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Daily File, 1950-1953 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Mainly a Daily File - but with other correspondence, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon
    - B-File, 1934-1954 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      British Museum, Bartram
    - Before Audubon, 1934-1941 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      Includes proposals for fellowships and grants as well as correspondence regarding publication
    - University of Chicago Press, 1941-1946 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      Includes reader feedback on manuscript
    - Before Audubon, 1942-1947 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Publication, 1946-1948 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Army Medical Library, 1947-1951 (Box 7, Folder 23)
      Regarding Volcher Coiter. Includes "A Sixteenth Century Classification f Birds" by Elsa Allen for the proceedings of the 10th International Ornithological Conference
    - Before Audubon, 1951-1956 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Letters of Congratulations and appreciation regarding the publication of The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon, 1951-1957 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Before Audubon, 1952-1955 (Box 7, Folder 26)
      Feedback and corrections
    - "Post Audubon" Study, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Second Volume Correspondence, (1938)1960-1968 (Box 7, Folder 28)
      Includes notes and
    - Russell and Russell Publishers Regarding the publication of The History of American Ornithology, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - John Abbot of Georgia
    - Babiy, Edith, 1956-1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Translations; Gesuer and Other Early Birds
    - British Museum regarding Abbot, 1939-1964 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Carnegie Museum - Regarding the Avinoff Portfolio of Abbot Drawings, 1946-1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Carson, Marion, 1954-1957 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Coolridge, Herman, 1953-1965 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Includes black and white prints of Abbot materials
    - DeLoach, R. J., (1924) 1953-1963 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Emory University - Abbot Sketchbook, 1954-1961 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Ewan, Joseph - Tulane University, 1956-1962 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Georgia Historical Society, 1952-1967 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Harris, Lucien, Jr., 1937-1957 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      John Abbot and the insects of Georgia
    - Jones, Frank Morton, 1956-1958 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Latham, John - research correspondence, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Sawyer, F.C. - British Museum regarding John Abbot, 1937-1959 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Scheetz, Francis, 1947-1957 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence Regarding the Publication of John Abbot Manuscript, 1951-1960 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Research and Publication Correspondence, 1956-1964 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence Regarding Publication of Manuscript, 1959-1967 (Box 8, Folder 17)
      Mainly with the University of Georgia Press
    - Royal Society, Frank Morton Jones and Carnegie Museum Regarding John Abbot, c. 1938-1953 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Early Correspondence Regarding John Abbot, 1939-1962 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence and Notes Regarding John Abbot (Some General Ornithology Correspondence), 1948-1955 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence Regarding John Abbot, 1956-1959 (Box 8, Folder 21)
      Note from Elsa Allen reads" Important Letters Re Abbot. Keep Handy"; kept in her order
    - Correspondence Regarding John Abbot, 1960-1968 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - General Research, undated (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Regarding the Publication of the Abbot Manuscript After Elsa Allen's Death, 1967-1976 (Box 8, Folder 56)
      Mills Lane IV, E M. Coulter, and Joseph Ewan
    - Alpha File
      - A - Correspondence, 1959-1967 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Abbot, John - Correspondence Regarding Publication, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - The Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia Regarding Alexander Wilson, 1940-1952 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - The Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia Regarding LeConte, 1958-1959 (Box 9, Folder 4)
        Originally with Dorothy Povey correspondence
      - Articles - Correspondence Regarding John Abbot, 1937-1957 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - B - Correspondence, 1958-1964 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Babiy, Edith Regarding John Abbot, 1954-1961 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Barrow, Elfrida Regarding John Abbot, 1956-1958 (Box 9, Folder 8)
        Originally with correspondence with Lalla Bell
      - Bartram, William - Correspondence Regarding Research, 1942, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Bartsch, Paul and Signe - Memories of a Carolina Parakeet, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 10)
        Includes black and white prints and a single 35mm slide
      - Basset, Anna Stowell Regarding John Abbot, c. 1938 (Box 9, Folder 11)
        Includes the article "Georgia Records of John Abbot" and "Chronology of John Abbot" by Anna Stowell Basset
      - Bell, Lalla Regarding John Abbot, c. 1956-1962 (Box 9, Folder 12)
        Originally with Correspondence with Elfrida Barrow
      - Bills and Study Expenses, 1961-1968 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Bissell, Theo. - University of Maryland Regarding John Abbot, 1952-1955 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Bovey, Dr. P. - Switzerland, 1939-1958 (Box 9, Folder 15)
        John Abbot of Georgia
      - British Museum of Natural History, 1935-1960 (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Bulletins, 1962-1965 (Box 9, Folder 17)
        News of Norway and Charles Lamb Society Bulletin
      - C - Correspondence, 1957-1962 (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Carnegie Museum, 1957-1960 (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Carnegie Museum, Cambridge, England and Dublin Museum Regarding John Abbot, 1952-1960 (Box 9, Folder 20)
        Also includes handwritten pages of John Abbot Manuscript
      - Cate, Margaret Regarding Samuel Wright, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - Catesby, William - Correspondence Regarding Research, 1934-1956 (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - Charleston Museum and other Correspondence from North and South Carolina Regarding John Abbot, 1952-1956 (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - Coolridge, Herman, 1956-1961 (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Davis, Ethel Regarding John Abbot, 1957-1959 (Box 9, Folder 25)
        Notes in German and French
      - DeLoach, R.J. H., c. 1955-1962 (Box 9, Folder 26)
      - Drury Papers - Correspondence and Notes, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 27)
      - Enquiries, 1939-1959 (Box 9, Folder 28)
      - Escher-Zollikofer, Heinrich - Research, 1956 and undated (Box 9, Folder 29)
      - Ewan, Joseph, Tulane University Regarding John Abbot and Louis Jean Pierre Vieillot, 1952-1959 (Box 9, Folder 30)
      - Expenses of study, 1952-1961 (Box 9, Folder 31)
      - F - Correspondence, 1953-1957 (Box 9, Folder 32)
      - Fellowships and Grants, 1938-1961 (Box 9, Folder 33)
        Includes photos of Elsa Allen
      - Francillon, John - Research Notes and Correspondence, 1948-1957 (Box 9, Folder 34)
      - Friedmann, Herbert, Smithsonian Institution Regarding John Abbot, 1957-1959 (Box 9, Folder 35)
      - G - Correspondence, 1933-1964 (Box 9, Folder 36)
      - Ganter, Herbert (College of William and Mary) and Gore, Belle, 1939-1959 (Box 9, Folder 37)
      - Georgia Department of Archives and History, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 38)
      - Georgia Historical Society, 1954-1960 (Box 9, Folder 39)
        Hawes, Lilla
      - Georgia Ornithological Society, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 40)
      - Georgia, University of, 1939-1958 (Box 9, Folder 41)
        Includes correspondence and notes on University of Georgia's Abbot materials
      - Georgia, University of, Press, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 42)
      - Grants, 1937-1951 (Box 9, Folder 43)
        American Philosophical Society and the National Science Foundation
      - Grants: Travel Notes and Correspondence, 1940-1965 (Box 9, Folder 44)
        England, Philadelphia and Cambridge (Harvard)
      - H - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 9, Folder 45)
      - Hargitt, Charles and Mary, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 46)
      - Harvard University and Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard, 1950-1961 (Box 9, Folder 47)
      - Henry, Josephine DeNancrede Regarding John Abbot Drawings, 1950-1957 (Box 9, Folder 48)
      - Hertzog, Friedrich Paul Von Wurttemberg, 1961-1963 (Box 9, Folder 49)
      - I - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 50)
      - Illustrations for The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon, c. 1951 (Box 9, Folder 51)
      - Illustrations for John Abbot - Notes, c. 1957 (Box 9, Folder 52)
      - Insects - John Abbot, 1937-1959 (Box 9, Folder 53)
        Royal Entomological Society, Royal Society, Carnegie Museum, Public Archives of Nova Scotia and the College of William and Mary
      - Insects - John Abbot, Carnegie Museum, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 54)
      - Kansas, University of, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 55)
      - Knosley Hall, 1954-1963 (Box 9, Folder 56)
      - L - Correspondence, 1952-1957 (Box 9, Folder 57)
      - Laboratory of Ornithology, c. 1958-1959 (Box 9, Folder 58)
        Includes an undated list of National Ornithology Faculty
      - Lanier, Maude Newton, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 59)
      - LeConte, John Eatton - Correspondence and Handwritten Manuscript, 1956-1960 (Box 9, Folder 60)
      - Lectures, 1939-1959 (Box 9, Folder 61)
      - Lectures, 1954-1960 (Box 9, Folder 62)
      - Linnaeus and Linnaean Society, London, 1932-1957 (Box 9, Folder 63)
        Includes the "Swedish Linnaeus Society Yearbook, 1932"
      - Lofthouse, Hilda, 1946-1959 (Box 9, Folder 64)
        Spider Manuscript, Elsa Allen
      - London, 1948-1957 (Box 9, Folder 65)
      - Longwood Library, Kennett Square, PA, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 66)
        DuPont and Abbot
      - McAtee, W. L., 1956-1958 (Box 9, Folder 67)
      - M - Correspondence, 1954-1960 (Box 9, Folder 68)
      - Murphy, Robert C., 1945-1962 (Box 9, Folder 69)
      - Museum National D'Histoire, Paris, France, 1953-1961 (Box 9, Folder 70)
      - Museums and Botanical Gardens, 1951-1953 (Box 9, Folder 71)
        American Museum of Natural History, Peale's Museum, and Duchess of Portland
      - National Science Foundation, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 72)
        Fellowship; other research correspondence
      - Newsom, Jesse and Elizabeth, 1954-1959 (Box 9, Folder 73)
      - O - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 74)
      - Oxford, 1939-1953 (Box 9, Folder 75)
      - P- Correspondence, c. 1958 (Box 9, Folder 76)
        Regarding Peale, Titian Ramsay
      - Personal Correspondence, c. 1950 (Box 9, Folder 77)
        Includes letters from Phoebe Allen
      - Photographs for Abbot Bok, 1950-1963 (Box 9, Folder 78)
      - Povey, Dorothy, Knowsley Hall, 1954-1956 (Box 9, Folder 79)
      - Publication, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 80)
        Includes outline of Abbot book submitted to Institute of Early American History and Culture
      - Reviews (Box 9, Folder 81)
        Written by Elsa Allen
      - S - Correspondence, 1953-1963 (Box 9, Folder 82)
      - Scheetz, Virginia, 1952-1957 (Box 9, Folder 83)
        Includes Correspondence regarding the John Abbot drawings owned by Josephine Henry
      - Shield, Phyllis W., Regarding Drury, 1950-1961 (Box 9, Folder 84)
        Regarding John Abbot and John Francillon; see also her letters regarding Francillon under his name
      - Song Birds of America - Bibliographic Cards, undated (Box 9, Folder 85)
      - Spillman, Ramsay, 1956-1959 (Box 9, Folder 86)
      - Stresemann, Erwin, 1953-1960 (Box 9, Folder 87)
        Regarding John Abbot materials in Berlin
      - Stringham, Emerson, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 88)
        Regarding John Abbot and Alexander Wilson
      - Stuart, Lyman and Eleanor, c. 1958-1959 (Box 9, Folder 89)
      - Stuart, Mary, undated (Box 9, Folder 90)
      - T - Correspondence, c. 1960 (Box 9, Folder 91)
      - Terres, Kenneth - Lippincott Nature Books, 1961-1966 (Box 9, Folder 92)
        Includes a list of publication by Elsa Allen
      - Tomkins, Ivan; Taub; Tate, Susan; and Thomas, Phyllis, 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 93)
      - Uggla, Arvid - University of Upsala, Sweden, 1950-1951 (Box 9, Folder 94)
        Regarding The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon
      - Van Nostrand Company, Inc., 1946 (Box 9, Folder 95)
      - Van Tyne, Josselyn - University of Michigan, 1952-1956 (Box 9, Folder 96)
      - Vieillot, Louis Jean Pierre, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 97)
      - Virginia - Research Regarding John Abbot, 1951-1957 (Box 9, Folder 98)
        Includes correspondence regarding Ganter, Herbert
      - W - Correspondence, 1935-1954 (Box 9, Folder 99)
      - War Office, London, 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 100)
        Also includes some correspondence from Povey, Dorothy
      - Weeks, Mangum, 1952-1965 (Box 9, Folder 101)
      - Wetmore, Alexander - Smithsonian Institution, 1919-1960 (Box 9, Folder 102)
        Includes letters from Wetmore to John P. Young
      - Wilson, Alexander, 1941-1962 (Box 9, Folder 103)
        Correspondence regarding research, publication and bonze cast; also includes a photograph of the Wilson statue with Elsa and Arthur Allen
      - Zimmer, John, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - Alexander Wilson and Mark Catesby
    - Correspondence Regarding Alexander Wilson, c. 1940-1956 (Box 7, Folder 30)
      Includes some manuscript materials including ""The Paisley Memorials to Alexander Wilson"
    - "A Letter from an American Visitor to Paisley to the Paisley Daily Express", May 1949 (Box 7, Folder 31)
      Regarding Wilson
    - Correspondence regarding Alexander Wilson, 1949-1959 (Box 7, Folder 32)
      Includes loose pages of manuscript and research notes
    - Alexander Wilson research Correspondence, 1941-1964 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Miller, James (Paisley ), 1953-1961 (Box 7, Folder 40)
      Found with the Notes from London 1934-1935
    - Alexander Wilson Statue Correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Research and Correspondence, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 35)
      Includes a handwritten copy of an article on Alexander Wilson from The Glasgow Herald from August 23, 1913
    - Mark Catesby Research, 1934-1962 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Mark Catesby research correspondence, 1934-1963 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Mark Catesby Research, 1948 and 1963 (Box 7, Folder 38)
      Includes a copy of Catesby's baptismal record "Mark Catesby and the Nomenclature of North American Birds by Whitmer Stone from the Auk 1929
    - Wrangham, C.E. regarding Mark Catesby, 1949-1953 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Photostates of Mark Catesby correspondence at the British Museum, undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Photostates of Mark Catesby correspondence at the British Museum, undated (Folder 2)
  - Fellowships and Grants
    - Application Material for Fellowships, 1932-1942 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Letter of recommendation for Alpha Omicron Pi Scholarship, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence and an Outline of The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon, 1933-1937 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Grant and Fellowship Materials, 1933-1953 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - American Council of Learned Societies, [1934] 1937 (Box 8, Folder 28)
      Plans of Study for The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon
    - Grants and Fellowships in Aid of Research, 1934-1953 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Grants and Fellowships in Aid of Research, 1934-1958 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Grants and Fellowships: Correspondence and Application Materials, 1935-1958 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence and Write-Up of Qualifications for Grants, 1936-1952 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Application material for an unknown grant or fellowship, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - The American Scandinavian Foundation - Application for a Grant, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - American Ornithologists Union Fellowship, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - "Biographical Materials" for Elsa Allen, c. 1952 (Box 8, Folder 36)
      Includes an "Account of the Advanced Work, Research and Creative Writing of the Applicant, Cornell University appointment letters and a list of recent publications by Elsa Allen
    - Announcement of Grant from the American Philosophical Society to Elsa Allen, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Arcadia Foundation Grant for Studies in the History of Ornithology, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - American Scandinavian Foundation, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 39)
      Includes a letter to "Doctor Steve" regarding her writing and desire to work on a more personal manuscript
    - National Science Foundation - Fellowships, 1956-1960 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Fellowships and Grants, 1956-1961 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - National Science Foundation Application Material for Second Volume of The History of Ornithology, c. 1956-1965 (Box 8, Folder 42)
      Includes Bibliography, and handwritten sections on Mark Catesby and Louis Jean Pierre Vieillot
    - National Science Foundation Report on Fellowship 1960, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Report on Post Doctorial Fellowship of the National Science Foundation, March-October 1961 (Box 8, Folder 44)
      Louis Jean Pierre Vieillot: Only a 3 handwritten pages within the notebook
    - Autobiographical sketch of Elsa Allen for grant application, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 45)
      Written in 1945 "now incomplete 1962"
    - Application for Grant Aid from the American Council of Learned Societies and Sections of Before Audubon Manuscript, undated (Box 8, Folder 46)
- Series III. Research and Manuscripts by Elsa Allen
  - Women's Issues
    - Rough Draft of a Manuscript on Women, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Minerva's Daughters - Original Manuscript (1), undated (Box 8, Folder 48)
      Title Page reads "Plastic Female: An Examination of Her Modern Status
    - Minerva's Daughters - Original Manuscript (2), undated (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Minerva's Daughters - Finished Draft: Pages 1-150, undated (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Minerva's Daughters - Finished Draft: Pages 1-60, undated (Box 8, Folder 51)
      Includes Table of Contents
    - Minerva's Daughters - Finished Draft: Pages 61-118, undated (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - Minerva's Daughters - Finished Draft: Pages 119-159, undated (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Minerva's Daughters - Manuscript Submitted to the Women's Press, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Mrs. or Ph.D.: A Mother Reports, Parts 1 and 2, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 55)
      Published in To Dragma journal of the Alpha Omicron Pi Fraternity
  - Chipmunk Study
    - Field Catalogue for Chipmunk Study, 1924-1925 (Box 2)
    - Field Catalogue for Chipmunk Study, 1925-1927 (Box 2)
    - Chipmunk Notes - Notebook, 1925 (Box 3)
    - Arthur Allen Biography Materials and Chipmunk Study Article, 1943 and 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Chipmunk Study Notes, 1924-1926 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Chipmunk Study Notes, 1925-1927 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Notes and Study Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Chipmunk Study, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Loose Page of Notes and Correspondence, 1928-1931 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Chipmunk Study Notes and Manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Handwritten
    - Chipmunk Study Notes and Loose Pages, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Includes a reprint of the article "Two New Siphonaptera From New York by M.A. Stewart
    - Loose Pages of Chipmunk Study Manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Typed and Handwritten
    - Pages 8-11 of Manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
      Typed
    - Studies in the Life History of the Eastern Chipmunk - Ph.D. Thesis, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - "Chipmunk Secrets" by Elsa Allen, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
      Includes photographs and other illustration
  - Bird Poetry
    - Draft of "Studies in Early American Bird Poetry" by Elsa Allen, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 12)
      "Submitted to the Faculty of the Graduate School of Cornell University in Partial Fulfillment of the Requirements for the Degree of Doctor of Philosophy"
    - Radio Talks by Elsa Allen and Bird Poetry, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Radio Talks by Elsa Allen and Bird Poetry, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)